<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apostles catechisme consisting of sixe articles, plainly expounded very profitable for all, but especially for the benefite of the vnlearned and those that desire more knowledge / by Iohn Foorthe, minister of the word of God.</title>
            <author>Foorthe, John, fl. 1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01022</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11128.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122635</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24478450</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24478450</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27718</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01022)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27718)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1851:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apostles catechisme consisting of sixe articles, plainly expounded very profitable for all, but especially for the benefite of the vnlearned and those that desire more knowledge / by Iohn Foorthe, minister of the word of God.</title>
                  <author>Foorthe, John, fl. 1623.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 71 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.L. for William Sheffard, and are to be sold at his shoppe, at the entring in of Popes head Allie out of Lumbard-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures:  A-D⁸ E⁷.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews VI, 1-2 --  Examinations, questions, etc.</term>
               <term>Catechisms, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27718:1"/>
            <p>THE APOSTLES CATECHISME CONSISTING OF SIXE ARTICLES, plainly expounded:</p>
            <p>Very profitable for All, but eſpecially for the benefite of the vnlearned and thoſe that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more Knowledge.</p>
            <p>By IOHN FOORTHE, Miniſter of the Word of God.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe, at the entring in of Popes head Allie out of Lumbard-ſtreet. 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27718:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27718:2"/>
            <head>To the Reuerend Father in GOD, <hi>Thomas Morton</hi> Doctor in Diuinitie, and Lord Biſhop of <hi>Couentrie</hi> and <hi>Lietchfield,</hi> I. F. wiſheth <hi>grace</hi> in this life, and <hi>glorie</hi> in the world to come.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREAS the holy Ghoſt hath both recorded in the ſixt Chapter of the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes, that ſhort Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, which the Apoſtles in their dayes taught thoſe whom they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the faith of Chriſt, &amp; alſo left the ſame to the Churches for all future times: I not doubting but that the euidence of the text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. and 6.1. Will iuſtifie this to bee the Apoſtles Catechiſme, haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to propound and expound
<pb facs="tcp:27718:3"/>the ſame as the Lord hath inabled mee, hoping thereby to whet vp their gifts, which are better able to adorne and enlarge it; to iuſtifie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Catechiſmes, which differing from this in words, agree with it in ſubſtance; and to propound it as a paterne or an example for imitation, that they which of themſelues are alreadie forward, may be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to proceede, and thoſe which are ſomewhat ſlacke, may bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked diligently to plant the firſt principles in the hearts of thoſe that are vnder their charge, and ſo yong plants may grow vp in their youth, and become worthie inſtruments in Church or Common-wealth, as God ſhall appoint. This ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe I haue preſumed to dedicate to your Lordſhips for theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe you are able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of the matter handled herein. Secondly, becauſe it hath beene
<pb facs="tcp:27718:3"/>publikely taught to youth in your Lordſhips Dioces. Thirdly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue great cauſe to giue ſome teſtimonie of heartie thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to your Lordſhips great fauour, which I haue lately found at your hands. And deſiring the ſmall te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie may bee accepted in good part, I ceaſe at this preſent. <hi>Iune</hi> 5. 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="catechism">
            <pb facs="tcp:27718:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27718:4"/>
            <head>THE APOSTLES CA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TECHISME.</head>
            <p>Queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVHat Principles of Religion will you ſpecially commend to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians that they may learne them perfectly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. They are thoſe which the Apoſtle commendeth to the Churches. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.1. therefore leauing the doctrine of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Chriſt, let vs goe on vnto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, not laying againe the foundation of repentance from dead workes, and of faith toward God, of the doctrine of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmes, and laying on of hands, and of the reſurrection from the dead, and of eternall iudgement.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How many are theſe in number?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> They are ſixe in number.</p>
            <p>Firſt, repentance from dead works.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:27718:5"/>
            <p>Secondly, faith towards God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the doctrine of baptiſme.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, impoſition of hands.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, reſurrection from the dead.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, eternall iudgement.</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>The firſt Article of repentance from dead workes.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>DEclare theſe more particularly in order, and firſt, what repentance from dead workes meaneth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> That this may be vnderſtood plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there are three things to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what workes are dead workes, and what workes are not dead works.</p>
               <p>Secondly, who muſt repent from dead works.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, how they muſt repent.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What workes call you dead workes, and what workes are not dead works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> For the clearer vnderſtanding of the point, we muſt conſider the works of men at three ſeuerall times, and according to the three diuers eſtates, or conditions of men in theſe three times.</p>
               <p>Firſt, before the fall of man.</p>
               <p>Secondly, after the fall of man.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27718:5"/>
               <p>Thirdly, after mans regeneration.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What were the workes of man before, and at his fall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The workes which <hi>Adam</hi> did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fall, were good and righteous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods will: but that worke which he did contrary to the will of God in eating the forbidden fruit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6. was a deadly worke, and procured death (that is, ſeparation from God. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18.) both to <hi>Adam,</hi> and to all his poſteritie. For firſt, God told <hi>Adam</hi> ſo before hand. <hi>Geneſis</hi> 2.17. Whenſoeuer thou eateſt thereof (that is, of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruite) thou ſhalt die the death. Secondly, the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, ſin when it is finiſhed bringeth death. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.15. Thirdly, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſinne is death: And that all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity both ſinned and dyed in <hi>Adam.</hi> It is manifeſt. Firſt, all mankind was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in <hi>Adam,</hi> as being then in his loines. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.28. When God ſaid to him: multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and repleniſh the earth: and therefore all mankind ſinned in <hi>Adam.</hi> For as <hi>Leui</hi> being in the loines of <hi>Abraham,</hi> payde tythes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. ver. 9, 10. ſo all mankind being yet in the loines of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſinned in <hi>Adam.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27718:6"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. By one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death paſſed vpon all men, for that all haue ſinned: thirdly, it is written. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. in <hi>Adam</hi> all die.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the workes of man after his fall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are altogether meere dead workes; for man being dead in ſinne. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ.</hi> 2.1. can doe no workes but dead workes, and ſuch as the tree is, ſuch are the fruits thereof. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.17. Wherefore the workes of all men fallen in by <hi>Adam,</hi> and not reconciled to God againe by faith in Chriſt, are dead workes, though they ſeeme neuer ſo glorious; before carnall men as the workes of Poets, Philoſophers, Orators, or whatſoeuer they bee that are not regenerate, as the Apoſtle ſheweth <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe.</hi> 2. ver. 11, 12. that they are without God in the world.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the workes of men regenerate and reconciled to God againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Their workes are neither dead workes, nor deadly workes, for hee that is borne of God ſinneth not. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. and 5.18.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How can that be ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, the Scripture witneſſeth that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27718:6"/>the regenerate ſinne: for here is no man that ſinneth not. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 8.46. Againe, it is written: <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 7.20. there is not a iuſt man vpon earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not. The Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, in many things we offend all. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.2. The Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith: if we ſay that we haue no ſinne, wee deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it may bee ſhewed by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Noah,</hi> that was drunken. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.21. of <hi>Abraham</hi> that lied twice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. ver. 13.18. <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.2. of <hi>Iſaak</hi> that lied alſo. <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.7. Of <hi>Lot</hi> that committed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſt in lying with his owne daughters, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.33, &amp;c. of the ſons of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who ſolde their brother <hi>Ioſeph. Gen.</hi> 37.27. of <hi>Reuben</hi> that lay with <hi>Bilhah</hi> his fathers Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine. <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.22. of <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> that treacherouſly ſlewe the <hi>Shechemites, Gen.</hi> 34.25. of <hi>Moſes</hi> that ſpake vnaduiſedly with his lips. <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.33. and was depriued of the land of <hi>Canaan. Numh.</hi> 20.12. As he complaineth. <hi>Deutr.</hi> 1.37. &amp; 4.21. &amp; 32.48. of <hi>Dauid</hi> that committed adultery and murther. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. of <hi>Salomon</hi> that loued ſtrange women, and followed after other Gods. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 11. of <hi>Peter</hi> that denyed Chriſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.70.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27718:7"/>and of others, that being regenerate, ſinne, and that there is no ſin, but one or other regenerate perſon hath fallen into it, (except the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt) and how ſay you then, or how ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> that hee which is borne of God ſinneth not. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. &amp; 5.18.</p>
               <p>A. Two anſwers may be giuen to this obiection.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaketh ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, that whoſoeuer is borne of God ſinneth not, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.9. &amp; 5.18. ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> anſwereth generally. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2. How ſhall we that are dead to ſinne, liue any longer therein.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the anſwer is more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and more directly anſwering to the obiection, that though the regenerate commit a ſinne which of it ſelfe and in his owne nature is deadly; yet it procureth not death to them, and that for theſe ſixe reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe they are quickened toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Chriſt. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.13. and this new life which the regenerate haue is in Chriſt. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11. whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.3. your life is hidden with Chriſt in God.</p>
               <p>Seeing then the life of the regenerate is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27718:7"/>not in themſelues, but in Chriſt (who dyeth no more, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9.) it cannot bee that their ſinne ſhould be deadly to procure death vnto them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, whereas the ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. Chriſt hath redeemed vs from the curſe of the Law, being made a curſe for vs. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. and therefore the workes of the regenerate are not deadly, neither doe they procure death, becauſe the curſe of the Law which ſtrengthened ſinne to procure death is taken away by Chriſt. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.14. See <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, although there be a continuall fight or combate betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit in the regenerate, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe the things which they would. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17. yet ſinne getteth not the dominion ouer them, becauſe they are not vnder the Law, but vnder Grace. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. and therefore ſinne woundeth them not to death.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, whiles the regenerate hauing ſinne dwelling in them, doe not the good which they would, but the euill which they would not. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15.19. It is not they that doe it, but ſinne that dwelleth in them: as the Apoſtie confeſſeth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27718:8"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.17.20. And therefore hee that is borne of God ſinneth not as the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.9. and 5.18.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, as in the time of the Law, there were expiations from ſinne by ſacrifices, and purgations from pollutions by water, ſo it was foretold. <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.1. that in the time of the Goſpel there ſhould be a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine opened to the houſe of <hi>Danid,</hi> and to the inhabitants of Ieruſalem, for ſinne and for vncleanneſſe. And in the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (the ratification whereof is largely declared, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. &amp;c.) the Apoſtle <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth that Chriſt the Mediatour of the new Teſtament, came both by water and alſo by blood. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.6. who by his blood entred in once into the holy place, hauing obtained eternall redemption for vs. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12. and cleanſed his Church with the waſhing of water by the word. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. And therefore we ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. that the blood of Chriſt, who through the eternall ſpirit of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered himſelfe without ſpot to God pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth our conſciences from dead workes to ſerue the liuing God. And the blood of Ieſus Chriſt purgeth vs from all ſinne. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, God hauing reconciled the elect
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27718:8"/>to himſelfe by the death of Chriſt, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not their treſpaſſes vnto them. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we conclude this point with the words of the Apoſtle. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. that there is no condemnation to the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate which are in Chriſt Ieſus, and which walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for the Lawe of the ſpirit of life which is in Chriſt Ieſus hath freede them from the law of ſinne and of death.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Which of theſe workes then muſt bee repented of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The ſecond ſort which were men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſixt queſtion, and which were done by men that were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes, for when they are effectually called from death to life in Chriſt, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate, then they muſt repent of their former dead workes before they be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. As for repentance for ſinne after baptiſme, we may ſpeake therof at another time.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Secondly, then tell me who thoſe are that muſt repent from dead workes, whether all Adams poſterity, who are all of them dead in ſinne, or ſome of them onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This queſtion may bee anſwered plainely and orderly in this manner.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:27718:9"/>
               <p>Firſt, God made this promiſe for the redemption of mankinde after they were all fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. The ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the head of the ſerpent.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſome men, by faith in Chriſt to come, imbraced this promiſe ioyfully, and ſhewed their faith as occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as did <hi>Abel,</hi> and all the faithfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. But ſome made no reckoning of that gratious promiſe, but through vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe reiected it as did <hi>Cain,</hi> and all other vnbeleeuers after him.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, God receiued into his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour againe, ſo many of <hi>Adams</hi> poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as beleeued his gratious promiſe, and ſhewed their faith in the promiſed ſeede of the woman as occaſion required, as hee receiued <hi>Abel</hi> and all the faithfull after him: But God reiected, and left ſtill in their ſinnes, and in the ſtate of death all thoſe that beleeued not that his gracious promiſe, as he left <hi>Cain,</hi> and an vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers after him.</p>
               <p>Hereof it is, that there were alwayes two ſorts of people in the world, beleeuers and vnbeleeuers; the Church of God, and the Synagogue of Satan; and as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <hi>Iſaak. Gen.</hi> 21.9. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.29. So the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27718:9"/>vnbeleeuers haue alwaies hated and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the faithfull.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What you haue ſaid hitherto, ſeemeth to bee of the time of the Law, and of the Church before Chriſt came in the fleſh; what ſay you of the time of the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> No other thing then hath beene ſaid of the time of the Law; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we wil repeate the ſame things againe in the ſame order.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſent to the Iewes only, publiſhed generally to all the Iewes, that gratious promiſe of redemption, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Repent yee, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen is at hand: and a little after,</hi> Math. 3.10. <hi>And now alſo the axe is laide vnto the roote of the trees: therefore euery tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is he wen downe, and caſt into the fire:</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection from the dead, Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles to publiſh this gracious promiſe of redemption to all people, as well Gentiles as Iewes, ſaying, Mark. 16.15. <hi>Goe ye into all the world, and preach the Goſpel to euery creature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, ſome reiected this glad tidings of ſaluation, both Iewes. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. <hi>(But the Phariſees and Lawyers reiected the counſell of God againſt themſelues, being
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27718:10"/>not baptized of him,)</hi> and alſo Gentiles, as the Philoſophers at <hi>Athens,</hi> ſaying of <hi>Paul: What will this babler ſay, Act.</hi> 17.18. but ſome beleeued both of the Iewes, and alſo of the Gentiles, as many as were ordained to ſaluation, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.48.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the beleeuers were recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into Gods fauour, into this new king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, and the vnbeleeuers were reiected, whether they were Iewes or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> receiued the belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Iewes, and baptized them. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.6. and reiected the vnbeleeuers. So did <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 2.38. Alſo <hi>Peter</hi> firſt receiued into the ſocietie of the Church, <hi>Cornelius</hi> and other beleeuing Gentiles. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.4. &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.7. Alſo other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Gentiles at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> were receiued into the Church of Chriſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 20, 21. &amp;c. Alſo at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidia,</hi> (<hi>Acts</hi> 13.14.) <hi>Paul</hi> receiued the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers both Iewes and Gentiles, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected the vnbeleeuing Iewes, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. <hi>It was neceſſarie that the word of God ſhould firſt haue beene ſpoken to you: but ſeeing yee put it from you, and iudge your ſelues vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of euerlaſting life; Loe, wee turne to the Gentiles.</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> did at <hi>Corinthus, Acts</hi> 18.6. and at <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 19.9.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:27718:10"/>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who then are they that muſt repent from dead workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two ſorts of perſons. Firſt, thoſe who hearing the promiſe of redemption by Chriſt, beleeue it, and ſo are conuerted and regenerate. Secondly, the children of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Who are they that beleeue the Goſpel, are regenerate, and muſt repent from dead workes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Though it might ſuffice to ſay, as before is ſaid, that it is all that beleeue in Chriſt, and none of the vnbeleeuers, yet hauing ſpeciall regard to the firſt prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel, it ſeemeth good to reduce all the faithfull to theſe two ſorts of men.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the remnant of the Iewes (<hi>Eſa.</hi> 10.22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.29.) that appertained to the election of grace, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5.) and were to be receiued into the couenant of the new Teſtament of Chriſts firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh and ſo to be ſaued, when the generall multitude of the other vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing Iewes, were to bee reiected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their vnbeleife (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.31.) this little remnant of the beleeuing Iewes, firſt repented of their dead workes before they were or could bee baptized by <hi>Iohn</hi> the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27718:11"/>
                  <hi>Baptiſt. Matth.</hi> 3.6. or by any other after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.38.</p>
               <p>Secondly, thoſe of the Gentiles, that by the preaching of the Goſpell, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to the faith of Chriſt. For thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented from their dead workes before they were receiued into the Chriſtian Church by Baptiſme, as the beleeuing Iewes acknowledged, ſaying: then hath God alſo to the Gentiles giuen repentance vnto life. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.18. And ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledgeth them to be of the Church. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.6. that the Gentiles ſhould be fellow heires, and of the ſame bodie, and partakers of his promiſe in Chriſt by the Goſpell. See alſo, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.11.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>You haue ſhewed that the beleeuing Iewes, and the beleeuing Gentiles repented from dead workes before they were baptized: ſhew me now how the children of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, being already receiued into the Church by Baptiſme, muſt repent from dead workes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> As the remnant of the elect Iewes and as the beleeuing Gentiles profeſſed their repentance before they were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed: ſo the children of the faithfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their repentance after baptiſme, for it is requiſite that they receiuing baptiſme (which is the ſeale of the couenant) in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27718:11"/>their infancie (becauſe of the promiſe of God made to their parents, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.) ſhould when they come to yeeres of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, learne the conditions of the couenant conteined in the firſt principles of religion, and then make open profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof in their owne perſon, that ſo the couenant betweene God and his Church may be continued from generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation. But of this profeſsion of the children of the faithfull, more ſhall be ſaid hereafter in the fourth Article.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Now that you haue ſhewed who muſt repent, tell me alſo how they muſt repent, as you promiſed in anſwering my third queſtion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three waies:</p>
               <p>Firſt, by lamenting and renouncing their former courſe of life, and former dead workes wherein they liued.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by preſent breaking off their ſinnes, and entring into a new kinde of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly life without any delay.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by promiſing faith and holy obedience to God for the reſt of their life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:27718:12"/>
               <head>The ſecond Article of faith toward God.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHat ſay you of faith toward God, which is the ſecond Article of the Apoſtles Catechiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what faith is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what God promiſeth.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what we muſt beleeue.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is faith, or how deſcribe you it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Faith (reſting vpon the promiſes of God declared in his word. <hi>Rom</hi> 10.17. is the ground of things hoped for, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of things not ſeene. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. for wee looke not at the things which are ſeene, but at the things which are not ſeene: for the things which are ſeene, are temporall, but the things which are not ſeene, are eternall. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. for eye hath not ſeene, care hath not heard, neither haue entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that loue him. 1. <hi>Corinthians</hi> 2.9. and therefore it is ſaid in an other place, we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27718:12"/>walke by faith and not by ſight.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What ſay you then of the promiſes which God hath made to his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what they are.</p>
               <p>Secondly, how God performeth them.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the promiſes which God hath made to his Church?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are of two ſorts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some to be performed in this life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some to be performed in the life to come.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What are the promiſes that belong to this life, and are in this life to be performed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are many, but I will mention onely foure.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is, that great and gratious promiſe of mans redemption, made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after the fall of <hi>Adam. Gen.</hi> 3.15. the ſeede of the woman ſhall breake the head of the Serpent and when the fulneſſe of time was come, performed by Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. but when the fulneſſe of time was come, God ſent forth his Sonne made of a woman, made vnder the law, to redeeme them that were vnder the Law, that wee might receiue the adoption of ſonnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſecond is, that he will make a ſpeciall and an euerlaſting couenant with
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27718:13"/>the faithfull, and with their ſeede after them to bee their God, and the God of their ſeede after them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The third is, that he will make the faithfull his peculiar people. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.5. Now therefore if yee will obey my voice indeede and keepe my couenant, then yee ſhall be a peculiar treaſure vnto me aboue all people, though all the earth be mine, which <hi>Moſes</hi> repeateth <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. &amp; 14.2. &amp; 26.18.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth is, that God will honour, bleſſe and proſper his faithfull flocke aboue all people in the world, in all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to this preſent life, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at large <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.3, &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1. &amp;c. which two chapters are worthie to be often read, and meditated vpon conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What be promiſes which God made to his choſen people for the life to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> They are exceeding great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, whereby in this life we be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the diuine nature. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. and at the generall reſurrection our mortall bodies ſhall be made immortall. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.42. &amp;c. and like to the glorious bodie of Chriſt. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. wee ſhall be free from all miſerie. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.4. We
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27718:13"/>ſhall be with Chriſt where he is, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.3. and 17.24. and ſee God as he is. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.2. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. and ſhall be euer with the Lord. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>And for this cauſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: godlines is profitable vnto all things, hauing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of this life that now is, and of that which is to come. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth God performe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This may be anſwered two waies. Firſt, more generally God performeth all his promiſes in Chriſt, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. for all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God in him are yea and in him, Amen. For by Chriſt we haue redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.13. and intereſt to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God, ſeeing Chriſt is heire of all things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by ſuch ordinarie meanes as God hath appointed both for temporall and alſo for eternall bleſsings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What ſay you in the third place con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our ſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we muſt beleeue in God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who of his meere mercy hath made vs theſe gratious promiſes, and not in idols that can doe nothing. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.28. <hi>Jerem.</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:27718:14"/>10.5. neither in ſecondary meanes, which God hath ordained, that wee ſhould vſe them, but not truſt in them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.7.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we muſt beleeue the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med promiſes mentioned before in anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to your fift and ſixt queſtion, that they ſhall be performed according as the Lord had promiſed them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe without faith we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God, nor obtaine his promiſes, and becauſe our faith is weake; wee muſt labour to confirme and ſtrengthen our faith in God and in his promiſes, that we may enioy his fauour, and receiue his promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How may we ſtrengthen our faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Three waies.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by reading and meditating vpon the word of God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by meditating vpon Gods fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by conſidering Gods power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth the reading of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture confirme our faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. By conſidering theſe three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the ſame word which beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. is ſufficient alſo to confirme and ſtrengthen faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that it is vnpoſsible, the word
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27718:14"/>of God ſhould fayle. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.6.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that heauen and earth ſhall ſooner paſſe away, then the words of God faile. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.18. &amp; 24.35. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.17.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How doth the conſideration of Gods fidelity ſtrengthen our faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Scripture witneſſeth, that God is true and faithfull in performing what he ſpeaketh, whether he promiſe mercy, or threatneth iudgements concerning his promiſed mercy, it is ſaid, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 89.34. that he will not breake his couenant, nor alter the thing that is gone out of his lippes: yea he ſaith, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 54.10. that the mountaines ſhall ſooner remooue out of their places, then his couenant made with his Church ſhal faile, alſo that the night &amp; the day ſhal ceaſe to be, rather then his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denant made to his Church ſhould faile. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 33.20. And though the Church faile in performing, yet God for his part will not faile, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.60. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3. for the gifts and calling of God are without repentance. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. Whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> aſſureth the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9. and the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.24. of their eternall ſaluation, becauſe God who had
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27718:15"/>called them, is faithfull.</p>
               <p>And concerning the threatned and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocable iudgements of God againſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinnets the Lord ſaith thus.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zephan.</hi> 2.2.</note> Though <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtood before me, yet my mind could not be toward this people. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 15.2. And in another place: Though theſe three men <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were in it, (that is in Ieruſalem) they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſnes. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.14. And in this caſe <hi>Samuel</hi> tolde <hi>Saul</hi> that the ſtrength (or externity, that is the God) of Iſrael will not lye, nor repent. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.29.</p>
               <p>Secondly, one example ſheweth the faithfulneſſe of God in performing his promiſe: for <hi>Sara</hi> receiued ſtrength to conceiue ſeede, and was deliuered of a child, when ſhe was paſt age, becauſe ſhe iudged him faithfull which had promiſed. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. How doth the conſideration of Gods power ſtrengthen our faith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Scripture teſtifieth that God doth whatſoeuer he will, but he is in one mind, and who can turne him, and what his ſoule deſireth, euen that he doth. <hi>Iob</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:27718:15"/>23.13. And againe, but our God is in the heauen, he hath done whatſoeuer he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.3. and 135.6.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the example of <hi>Abraham</hi> ſheweth it, for hee at three ſeuerall times conſidering the omnipotent power of God, was confirmed and incouraged to beleeue the promiſes of God.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when God promiſed to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that though hee was then childleſſe, and without hope of children. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.2. yet his ſeede ſhould bee as the ſtarres of heauen for multitude. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5. then <hi>Abraham</hi> aboue hope beleeued vnder hope, that he ſhould be the father of many nations. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.18.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when God promiſed to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> being almoſt an hundereth yeeres old, that he ſhould haue a ſonne by <hi>Sara</hi> his wiſe. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.16. and 18.10, &amp;c. then did not he doubt of the promiſe of God through vnbeliefe, but was ſtrengthened in the faith, and gaue glory to God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully aſſured that hee which had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed was alſo able to doe it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.20.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, when God commanded <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> to offer vp his ſonne <hi>Iſaack. Gen.</hi> 22.2. Then <hi>Abraham</hi> offered vp his onely begotten ſonne of whom it was ſaid, that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27718:16"/>in <hi>Iſaak</hi> ſhall thy ſeede be called. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.17. becauſe he conſidered that God was able to raiſe him vp euen from the dead. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19.</p>
               <p>Then faith leaning vpon Gods word, truth and power comforteth the godly in this preſent life at all times, and aſſureth them of reſurrection to immortality at the day of iudgement, as <hi>Iob</hi> chap. 19.25. and <hi>Dauid Pſal.</hi> 16.9. openly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>The third Article of the doctrine of Baptiſme.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw will you declare this third Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by ſhewing what baptiſme is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by ſhewing what God doth in baptiſme?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by ſhewing what man doth in baptiſme?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. It is the Sacrament of regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (<hi>Iohn</hi> 3.5.) by the waſhing of water
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27718:16"/>through the word (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26.) and the renuing of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What doth God in baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> God baptizeth or waſheth a man from his ſinnes two wayes: for as in the time of the law there was a twofold cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,
<note place="margin">Rom. 4.15. Rom. 2. ver. 28.29.</note> one made inwardly in the heart without hands, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 10.16. <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11.) and another made with hands outwardly in the fleſh. (<hi>Gen.</hi> 17.11.) ſo there is alſo a twofold baptiſme, one inward in the heart, and an other out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What is the inward Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. It is the inward purging, purifying, and cleanſing of the heart from ſinne by faith in Chriſt, for when God calleth any effectually to ſure and certaine hope of ſaluation by the outward miniſtery of his word, and by the inward working of his ſpirit, then he begetteth in them a liuely faith in Chriſt, and ſo purifieth their hearts by faith, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> and other Gentiles whom he had conuerted and baptized, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.44. &amp;c. witneſſeth, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.9. ſaying, And he put no difference betweene vs and them, after that by faith he had purified their hearts, for whoſoeuer beleeueth ſhall be ſaued.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27718:17"/>
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. And the blood of Ieſus Chriſt his Sonne cleanſeth vs from all ſinne, 1. <hi>John</hi> 1.17. And they that are once purged haue no more conſcience of ſinne, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.2. And Chriſt ſaith: Bleſſed are the pure in heart. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.8. for this inward baptiſme conſiſteth not in the putting (or waſhing) away of the filth of the fleſh, but in that a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence maketh requeſt to God. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</p>
               <p>This inward baptiſme is proper to the elect onely, for no man knoweth it, but he that hath it. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.17. and a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger doth not intermeddle with his ioy. <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.10. The naturall man perceiueth it not. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the outward Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The anſwer may be deliuered more fully in theſe foure words.</p>
               <p>Firſt, it is the outward purging or wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing away of the filth of the fleſh with water, and an outward Sacrament of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, ſealing vp the faith of him that before was inwardly baptized in his heart by faith in Chriſt, for as the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sacrament of circumciſion was vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> a ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of faith which hee had when he was vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27718:17"/>
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. euen ſo outward baptiſme, is a ſeale of the faith of him that before was inwardly baptized or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in his heart by faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, outward baptiſme is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all that are in the viſible Church, whether they be good corne or tares, wiſe or fooliſh virgins, ſheepe or goates, true beleeuers or diſſembling hypocrites: for <hi>Iſhmael</hi> was circumciſed as well as <hi>Iſaak,</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> as well as <hi>Iacob: Iudas</hi> the tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour was baptiſed as well as the other A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> as well as the beleeuing Samaritanes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, outward baptiſme is ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to all, and for all in the viſible Church, that the Lord threatneth to cut him off fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people that deſpiſeth it. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14. becauſe he hath broken his couenant; for as the Lord offereth and promiſeth mercy, ſo hath he alſo ordeined the means of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, &amp; he that deſpiſeth the means, deſpiſeth alſo the mercy. Wherefore as they that were polluted and vncleane, waſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in water, that they might be cleane: as <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Sirian</hi> waſhed himſelfe in <hi>Iordan</hi> that he might be cleanſed from his Leproſie: and as the blind man waſhed his eyes in the poole of <hi>Siloam</hi> that he might receiue his ſight. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.7. ſo outward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:27718:18"/>muſt be vſed that wee may haue the inward purification of the heart.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, outward baptiſme is not ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that whoſoeuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, ſhould alſo want the mercy of God for ſaluation: for it is not the bare want of outward baptiſme which depriueth men of Gods mercy, but the contempt or neglect thereof when God requireth it and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth opportunity, that we may haue it. For then is the meanes of mercy deſpiſed, or little regarded, but when conueniently it cannot be had, no danger comes to them that want it, for the children which were borne to the Iſraelites, all thoſe fortie yeares of their wanderings in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, were not circumciſed, till they came into the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> as it appeareth. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 5. verſ. 2.5. The reaſon thereof was, becauſe the Iſraelites were not certen to reſt any time whiles they were in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, but whenſoeuer the piller of cloude by day, and of fire by night, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued then the Iſraelites, were to follow it as it appeareth. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.21. and 40.36. <hi>Num.</hi> 9.29. But if their children had been circumciſed, they could not haue beene fit and able to remooue, or to haue beene carried after the pillar of clouds before
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27718:18"/>ſuch time as they had beene whole againe, as we may ſee by example of the <hi>Sheche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> whom <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> ſlew when they were newly circumciſed, and ſo vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fight for their liues. <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.25. And God would not haue their children cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed thoſe forty yeares in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, becauſe it might haue beene dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to their liues: for the Lord will haue mercy and not ſacrifice. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.7. If a Chriſtian woman be deliuered of a childe among infidels, the baptizing of the child muſt be deferred till there bee opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What doth man in Baptiſme?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Man doth three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he ioyfully and thankefully recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the outward Sacrament of baptiſme, as the ſeale of Gods couenant, and as the ſeale of his inward baptiſme by faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he is preſently dead to ſinne, and preſently aliue, or raiſed vp vnto new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of life, as it may bee ſhewed thus in theſe two ſentences.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they that are regenerate, and made new or ſpirituall men in Chriſt, are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.30. and therefore:</p>
               <p n="1">1. They are crucified with him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27718:19"/>2. They are dead with him. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.20.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are buryed with him. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Quickened together with Chriſt. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.13. &amp; 3.1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Apoſtle ſaith plainely. <hi>Rom</hi> 6. verſe 3. know ye not that we which haue been baptized into Ieſus Chriſt, haue beene baptized into his death.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 4. We are buried then with him by baptiſme into his death, that like as Chriſt was raiſed vp from the dead by the glory of the Father, ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newnes of life.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 5. For if we be grafted with him to the ſimilitude of his death, euen ſo ſhall we be to the ſimilitude of his reſurrection. Hereupon, it is that the Apoſtlea litle after concludeth, that we are dead to ſinne, but aliue to God in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. for they are paſſed from death to life. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.24.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they that are thus preſently dead to ſinne and preſently aliue to God in baptiſme, doe for the reſt of their life, afterwards continually put off the olde man, till the body of ſinne bee deſtroyed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. and put on the new man till they become perfect men in Chriſt. <hi>Eph.</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:27718:19"/>4.13. And becauſe the true life of true religion ſtandeth in dayly putting off the old man, and putting on of the new man, it ſeemeth requiſite to ſhew in a word or twaine what the old man, and what the new man is.</p>
               <p>The olde man. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.22.
<note place="margin">The old man.</note> called alſo the naturall man. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. the fleſh. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.6. and the body of ſinne. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. conſiſteth in theſe foure things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Blindneſſe in vnderſtanding. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Frowardnes in will. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Boiſterouſnes in affection. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Act.</hi> 7. verſ. 54.57.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Diſobedience in actions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>Some parts of the old man are mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. ver. 19. adultery, fornication; vncleannes, laſciuiouſnes.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 20. Idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulation, wrath, ſtrife, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hereſies.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 21. Enuy, murthers, drunkennes, gluttonie, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Alſo theſe parts of the olde man are mentioned. <hi>Col.</hi> 3. verſ. 5. fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, inordinate affection, euill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27718:20"/>and couetouſnes.</p>
               <p>Verſ. 8. Wrath, anger, maliciouſneſſe, curſed ſpeaking, filthy ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>And theſe. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.31. bitternes, anger, wrath, crying, and euill ſpeaking.</p>
               <p>See more, <hi>Rom</hi> 1. verſ. 29, 30. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. ver. 9, 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3.</p>
               <p>The mortifying, crucifying, ſubduing, killing, and forſaking of theſe and ſuch like, is the putting off of the old man.</p>
               <p>The new man.
<note place="margin">The new man.</note> 
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. called alſo the ſpiritual man. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. hath;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Cleare vnderſtanding, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. ver. 10.12.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A ready will <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Sanctified affection. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Holy obedience. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.17.</p>
               <p>Some parts of this new man are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. <hi>Gal</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Verſe 22. Loue, ioy, peace, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, gentlenes, goodnes, faith.</p>
               <p>Verſe 23. Meekenes, temperance, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Alſo theſe parts of the new man are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Verſe. 11. Tender mercy, kindneſſe, humblenes of mind, meeknes, long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:27718:20"/>
               <p>Verſe 13. Forbearing one another, and forgiuing one another, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>He that after baptiſme followeth theſe things, and all other ſuch like, putteth on Chriſt. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. and putteth on the new man, which after God is created in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and true holineſſe. <hi>Ephſ.</hi> 4.24.</p>
               <p>And whiles true Chriſtians endeauour dayly to put off the old man, and to put on the new man, there is a continuall combate betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, as the Apoſtle ſheweth. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</p>
               <p>The combate, which is in the naturall man, is betweene reaſon guided by the light of nature, and the will ouerſwayed with the violence of affections.</p>
               <p>Baptiſme thus briefly noted, is the very fountaine of regeneration. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is the true death of the old man, and the true life of the new man, the old man dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decaying till he be deſtroyed, the new man daily growing till hee come to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Chriſt. For as when the Hen ſitteth vpon her egges and warmeth them, the egge is daily more and more corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the chicken formed and quickened till hee hath life and perfection; euen ſo when the ſpirit of God warmeth the hearts
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27718:21"/>of thoſe that are regenerate and baptiſed, the old man daily dyeth and is deſtroyed, and the new man is quickened till hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a perfect man in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>And when the power of baptiſme was better knowen and practiſed in the purer times before contentions bred herefies, and before Popiſh darkeneſſe ouer-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed religion, it brought foorth much holineſſe of life in the Churches with great feare and reuerence, which Satan enuying ſowed theſe two ſortes of tares in the Church to hinder the growth thereof.</p>
               <p>Firſt, ſome profeſſed ſo much holineſſe that they ſaid, that if a man ſinne openly after baptiſme, hee may not bee receiued into the viſible Church againe, and bee counted to bee of the ſocietie of the Saints.</p>
               <p>This hereſie partly then was, and yet is held of diuers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nouatus</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> held it about the yere after Chriſt 220.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meletius</hi> maintained the ſame in <hi>Egypt</hi> about the yeere 286.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Donatiſt</hi> in <hi>Afrike</hi> fauoured this opinion about the yere 298.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Luciferians</hi> in <hi>Sardinia</hi> were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with this opinion.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:27718:21"/>
               <p>The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> at this day differ little from it.</p>
               <p>But to anſwere thoſe men in a word.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, they dreame of a preſent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection after baptiſme, for which there is no warrant.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly they conſider not that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.17. there is a continuall combate betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit in them which are regenerate and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly they conſider not that there is remiſsion of ſinne after baptiſme, as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, if any man ſinne wee haue an aduocate with the Father, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>Secondly, other fearing to ſinne after baptiſme, would not bee baptized till they ſuppoſed death was at their doores to call them out of this life.</p>
               <p>But theſe conſider not:</p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſo they may die vnbapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That they incurre Gods diſpleaſure, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.14.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That they refuſe to bee Chriſtian ſouldiers, to fight Chriſts battell till it bee to late.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That there is remiſsion of ſinne af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27718:22"/>baptiſme. <hi>Zachar.</hi> 13.1. &amp; 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2. ver. 1.2.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That they deferre and neglect the meanes of grace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>The fourth Article of impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw will you declare the meaning of this fourth article?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by ſhewing the diuers vſe of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of hands.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by ſhewing what is meant in this place by impoſition of hands.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, by ſhewing the practiſe of this impoſition of hands.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How hath impoſition of hands beene vſed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, men by Gods appointment haue vſed by impoſition of hands to remoue and put from themſelues to another that which was grieuous and burdenſome vnto them, as for example, when any man ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the time of the Law, and was ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27718:22"/>from God after a ſort, and for the time, that hee might put away this bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of ſinne from himſelfe, and be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God againe, hee was to bring his ſacrifice and to lay his hands on the head of the beaſt, that was to be ſacrificed, and ſo lay vpon the beaſt the curſe of the Law, or the puniſhment due to him for his ſinne as it is generally noted, <hi>Leuit.</hi> 1.4. and particularly when ſinne was committed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the high Prieſt. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4. ver. 3.4.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The whole congregation. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4. verſe. 13.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ruler. <hi>Leu.</hi> 4. verſe 22.24.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A priuate perſon. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 4. verſe 27.29.</p>
               <p>When the firſt borne ſonnes of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael being choſen of God. <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.2. to miniſter to him in holy things: <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.22. and 24.5. were by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment to transferre this burthenſome function from themſelues to the <hi>Leuites,</hi> they did it by impoſing their hands vpon them. <hi>Num.</hi> 8.10. but whether this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may bee referred to this place, or to the ſecond which now followeth, let the wiſe iudge.</p>
               <p>Secondly, men by Gods appointment haue vſed by impoſition of hands to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:27718:23"/>grace vpon others, euen the graces of God; for ſometimes God himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth his graces vpon whom hee will, when he will, and how hee will.</p>
               <p>And ſometimes God maketh ſuperiours to be as it were his treaſurers, or ſtewards to conferre and beſtow his graces vpon their inferiours, as hee appointeth them. And ſuperiours being Gods treaſurers or ſtewards haue by Gods direction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred Gods graces vpon their inferiours diuers &amp; ſundry wayes, by diuers meanes, of which meanes it may ſuffice to mention three onely.</p>
               <p>Firſt, by annoynting them with that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oyle mentioned. <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.23. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with were annointed theſe three perſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Prieſts: <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.30. &amp; 29.7. <hi>Leuie.</hi> 8.12.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Kings. 1. <hi>Samuel:</hi> 16. verſ. 1.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Prophets. 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 19.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105.15.</p>
               <p>But this annointing with materiall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oile was a type of the graces of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, was vſed in the time of the Law onely, and now ceaſeth vnder the Goſpel, for Chriſt our onely and eternall high Prieſt, was annointed with the holy Ghoſt: <hi>Act.</hi> 10.38. without meaſure: <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.34.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27718:23"/>and of his fulneſſe all wee receiue. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.16.</p>
               <p>Secondly, by prayer, ſuperiours haue beſtowed Gods bleſsings vpon their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. Thus <hi>Iſaac</hi> beſtowed the bleſsing vpon <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 27.30. &amp;c. and <hi>Iacob</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſonnes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p>And the Prieſts ordinarily bleſſed the congregation of Iſrael at the end of Gods worſhip, when they diſmiſſed the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6.24,</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſuperiours beſtow the grace of the holy Ghoſt vpon their inferiours, both by prayer and impoſition of hands. And where laying on of hands is onely mentioned, there we muſt alſo vnderſtand that prayer is vſed.</p>
               <p>And this impoſition of hands with prayer, is two wayes to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as it belongeth to ſome ſpeciall perſons in a peculiar ſort.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as it belongeth to all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans generally.</p>
               <p>The ſpeciall perſons on whom hands haue beene layd in ſome ſpeciall manner, and for ſome ſpeciall cauſe, are theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the two ſons of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> on whom <hi>Iacob</hi> layd his hands, and bleſſed them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:27718:24"/>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Ioſhua</hi> on whom the Lord commaunded <hi>Moſes</hi> to lay his hands, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.18. when hee was to ſucceede <hi>Moſes</hi> in the gouernement of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. And ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> layd his hands vpon him, and gaue him a charge, <hi>Num.</hi> 27.23. And <hi>Ioſhua</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nun</hi> was full of the ſpirit of wiſedome, for <hi>Moſes</hi> had laid his hands vpon him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.9.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, thoſe that haue beene called to any publique function in the Church, haue beene thereunto appointed by laying on of hands and prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1 When the holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> for the worke wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I haue called them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. Then the Church which was at <hi>Antioch</hi> faſted and prayed, and layd their hands vpon them, and ſent them away, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2 When the diſciples had choſen thoſe ſeauen Deacons, then the Apoſtles prayed and laid their hands on them, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6.</p>
               <p n="3">3 When <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> ordained Elders in the Churches which were at <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, Iconium</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> they prayed with faſting, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. And laid hands on them, as it is probable: firſt, becauſe the word heere vſed <hi>Cheirotonea</hi> ſignifieth to ordaine, by impoſition of hands: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27718:24"/>becauſe Ordination was vſed with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands, as it appeareth, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.6. and 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Timotheus</hi> choſen to be an Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. and 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. was ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with impoſition of hands, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. and 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</p>
               <p>Thus much for impoſition of hands vpon ſome ſpeciall perſons.</p>
               <p>Secondly, then impoſition of hands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to all Chriſtians, that after Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme handes be layd vpon them, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, now it ſhall be ſhewed. For the former, impoſition of hands vpon ſome ſpeciall perſons, belongeth not to this place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. but that which is common vnto all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>You haue ſhewed, that impoſition of hands hath beene diuerſly vſed, and that to this fourth Article belongeth, that onely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands which is common to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: proceede therefore, and ſhew what this impoſition of hands is which belongeth to all Chriſtians?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is an ordinance of Chriſt in the new Teſtament, that al Chriſtians baptized might by impoſition of hands and prayer, receiue either the outward extraordinarie gifts, or els the inward ordinary graces of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27718:25"/>the holy ghoſt; as the practiſe wil fully ſhew</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Shew mee then what the practiſe thereof hath beene, and is or ſhould be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> This may be ſhewed fully in foure ſeuerall times.</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the dayes of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the pure times following for the ſpace of foure hundred yeares, or thereabouts.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in the time of Popiſh darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, in theſe laſt times ſince God reſtored to his Churches the light of the Goſpel more gloriouſly</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was the practiſe of this impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands in the Apoſtles dayes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Thoſe which in the Apoſtles daies were conuerted, either from Iudaiſme, to Chriſtianiſme, or from Gentiliſme to the faith of Chriſt receiued after baptiſme the outward extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt by prayer and impoſition of hands; as by theſe foure examples following it may plainely appeare.</p>
               <p>Firſt, when <hi>Peter</hi> had conuerted three thouſand at one Sermon, he promiſed the extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt, if they would repent, and be baptized, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Repent and be baptized euery one of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27718:25"/>you, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for the remiſsion of ſinnes, and yee ſhall receiue the gift of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. And that this promiſe was to be performed by prayer and impoſition of hands, the two following examples doe ſhew.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when <hi>Philip</hi> had conuerted the Samaritans. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.5. &amp;c. then <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſent by the Apoſtles from Ieruſalem. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.14. prayed for them, and laid their hands vpon them, and they receiued the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.15. who when they were come downe, prayed for them, that they might receiue the holy Ghoſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. then laid they their hands on them, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, thoſe twelue diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whom <hi>Apolloes</hi> as it ſeemed had baptized a little before, receiued the extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt, when <hi>Paul</hi> prayed for them and layed his hands vpon them. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.6. And when <hi>Paul</hi> had layed his hands vpon them, the holy Ghoſt came on them, and they ſpake with tongues, and propheſied.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Apoſtle writeth thus to the Galatians, this onely would I know of you, receiued yee the ſpirit, by the works of the law, or by the hearing of faith. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. In
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27718:26"/>which words it is manifeſt that the Galati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans receiued the ſpirit; that is to ſay, the extraordinary gifts of the ſpirit, when the Goſpell was preached vnto them, and when they beleeued in Chriſt. And though in this place, there be no mention of prayer and impoſition of hands, yet the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer examples ſhew that the Apoſtles ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily vſed prayer and impoſition of hands, when they gaue thoſe extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.18.</p>
               <p>And if there be a ſcruple or queſtion in any man to doubt or demand, how it came to paſſe that <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and his company re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt, before they were baptized, and without prayer and impoſition of hands. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. the anſwer is, that though Chriſt commanded his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel to euery creature, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of Iewes or Gentiles, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.15. yet neither <hi>Peter</hi> vnderſtood this. <hi>Act.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.19, 20. nor the other Apoſtles and brethren of the Iewes at Ieruſalem. <hi>Act.</hi> 11. <hi>verſe</hi> 1, 2.19. And therefore whiles <hi>Peter</hi> was preaching to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his company it pleaſed God to ſend thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt vpon <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his company, that <hi>Peter</hi> and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27718:26"/>all other Iewes might know that God had now receiued the Gentiles alſo into his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, into his Church as <hi>Peter</hi> and other Iewes acknowledge. <hi>Act.</hi> 11.17.</p>
               <p>And in this place wee muſt obſerue and remember, that theſe extraordinary gifts of the holy Ghoſt ſerued (as other workes miracles did alſo,) for theſe three purpoſes eſpecially.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to confirme the doctrine of the Goſpel, which at the firſt began to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Lord, and was confirmed to vs by them that heard him, God alſo bearing them witneſſe, both with ſignes and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and with diuers miracles, and gifts of the holy Ghoſt, according to his owne will, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3, 4.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to prooue the Apoſtles to bee ſent immediately from God to preach the Goſpel and to plant Churches, for by ſignes <hi>Paul</hi> prooueth himſelfe to be an Apoſtle. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. Truly the ſignes of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle were wrought among you in all pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in ſignes and wonders and mightie deedes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to make it manifeſt, that thoſe were Gods peculiar people, to whom hee gaue thoſe extraordinarie gifts of the holy Ghoſt; thus <hi>Peter</hi> knew that <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27718:27"/>thoſe that were with him, being all of them Gentiles, were acceptable to God, as hee confeſſeth, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.8. and other beleeuing It wes acknowledge, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.18.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was the practiſe of impoſition of hands in thoſe foure hundreth yeares after the Apoſtles dayes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. When thoſe extraordinarie outward gifts of the holy Ghoſt ceaſed, after that they had confirmed the doctrine, iuſtified the Apoſtles, and inlarged the Churches, then thoſe baptized and catechized perſons, on whom the Gouernours of the Church layd their hands and prayed for them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ordinarie inward graces of the holy Ghoſt, in a greater meaſure, for if any man haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, hee is none of his, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. See 2. <hi>Corint.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Galat.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>And they that are throughly acquainted with the ſtorie and ſtate of the Church, can make a full declaration heereof for theſe foure hundred yeares: but, as much heate cannot be receiued from a little fire, nor much water drawne out of a litle fountaine: ſo muſt I content my ſelfe with a few teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to manifeſt the practiſe for theſe foure hundred yeares; and namely with theſe fiue:</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:27718:27"/>1 Firſt, <hi>Tertullianus lib. de baptiſmo</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ann.</hi> 21<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>debinc manus imponitur, &amp;c.</hi> that is, after baptiſme there followeth impoſition of hands, and prayer is made to GOD, that they may receiue the holy Ghoſt, that is, more grace; for when the Elect are bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, they receiue the holy Ghoſt, but when they haue learned their Catechiſme, hands are layd vpon them, and prayer is made for them, that they may receiue encreaſe of grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ann.</hi> 250</note> 
                  <hi>Cyprianus</hi> writing to <hi>Iaha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> ſaith thus of impoſition of hands af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter baptiſme: <hi>Quod nunc quoque apud nos geritur, &amp;c.</hi> that is, Which thing wee alſo obſerue at this day, that they which haue beene baptized before, are afterward offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Gouernours of the Church, and by our prayers, and laying on of hands, they receiue the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ann.</hi> 390</note> 
                  <hi>Hieronymus aduerſus Lucife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianos. cap.</hi> 4. writeth thus: <hi>An neſcis etiam eccleſiarum hunc eſſe morem, &amp;c.</hi> that is, Knoweſt thou not that this is the cuſtome of the churches, to lay hands on them which were baptized before, and ſo praier is made that they may receiue the holy Ghoſt. Doſt thou require where this is written? It is written in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:27718:28"/>there were no Scripture for it, the generall conſent of the Churches might ſuffice.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Fourthly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ann.</hi> 39 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtinus libr.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>de baptiſmo contra Donatiſtas,</hi> ſhewing the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene the extraordinarie gifts of the holy Ghoſt: which were giuen to the baptized in the Apoſtles dayes, and the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie inward graces which were giuen af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in the ages following, by laying on of hands and prayer, ſaith thus: <hi>Neque enim temporalibus &amp; ſenſibilibus miraculis, &amp;c.</hi> that is, The holy Ghoſt is not now adayes giuen extraordinarily, as formerly it was giuen by impoſition of hands, ſeeing thoſe extraordinarie gifts ſerued then for confirmation of the Goſpell, and for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the Church. For who doth now expect, that they on whom hands are layd, that they may receiue the holy Ghoſt, ſhould ſodainely beginne to ſpeake Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. But it is vnderſtood by the bond of peace, that diuine charitie is ſecretly and inuiſibly inſpired into their hearts, that they may ſay, becauſe the loue of God is ſhed in our hearts by the holy Ghoſt which is giuen vs, &amp;c. alſo <hi>Auguſtinus lib.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>de Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate</hi> witneſſeth the continuance of this cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ome of laying on of hands, aſcribing the grace rather to prayer.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:27718:28"/>5. Fiftly, <hi>Eucherius</hi> cited by the Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riators of <hi>Magdeburg. Centur.</hi> 5 <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 657. ſaith thus: the party baptized is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a burnt ſacrifice, when by impoſition of hands he receiueth the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What was thirdly done in the time of Popery?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the ages following, this diuine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of confirmation by impoſition of hands and prayer, was diuers wayes abuſed by the Papiſts, as all other things were.</p>
               <p>Firſt, this impoſition of hands was made greater then baptiſme by Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the third of that name, as <hi>Bale</hi> writeth in his life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Papiſts ignorant of inward grace annointed the forehead of him that was confirmed with their holy oyle, as the Centuriators write. <hi>Centur.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 148.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Godfathers were required at confirmation, when the children to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed were able to anſwer for themſelues. <hi>Centur.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Col.</hi> 237.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, the Papiſts made confirmation a ſacrament. <hi>Petr. Lomb. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>dict.</hi> 7. <hi>Bellar. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>de confirmatione, cap.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What was fourthly done in theſe laſt times, when it pleaſed God to deliuer his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27718:29"/>Church out of Popiſh thraldome, and reſtore the light of the Goſpel againe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The Lord raiſed vp many worthy men which diſcouered the falſe doctrines and practiſes of popery, and reduced the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of Chriſt to their former integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and amongſt the reſt this alſo of confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: as namely, <hi>Caluin. inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 19. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4. and in his Commentaries vpon <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in his Common Places. <hi>Claſſ.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 14. and <hi>Chemnici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> who in his ſecond part of the examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Tridentine Concil.</hi> rehearſeth ſixe points of this confirmation as they were propounded in the aſſembly at <hi>Ratiſphone</hi> in the yeare. 1541. Of which aſſembly <hi>Sleuian</hi> alſo maketh mention in the latter end of his thirteenth booke of Commentaries, and in the beginning of his fourteenth booke, and the ſixe points of confirmation then propounded, and ſince rehearſed by <hi>Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicius,</hi> are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, the child that was baptized in his infancy, and now hauing learned his Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e confirmed, is admoniſhed how and to what end he was baptized, how then God ſealed vp vnto him the couenant and promiſe of peace and grace, and how he himſelfe renounced Satan, profeſſed his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27718:29"/>faith, and promiſed obedience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, the child in his owne perſon, and before the whole Church made publike profeſsion of the dectrine, and of his owne faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the child is queſtioned con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſome chiefe points of Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whereunto he anſwereth, and if hee vnderſtand them not ſufficiently, he is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtructed therein.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, the child is further admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that in this his profeſsion hee would further declare that hee diſſenteth from all heathen, hereticall and profane opinions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, he is ſeriouſly admoniſhed and exhorted out of the word of God, to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere in the couenant of baptiſme in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and faith which he hath profeſſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Sixtly, there are hands laid vpon the child, and earneſt prayer is made to God, that he would giue him his holy Spirit for his further confirmation in that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and faith, and this prayer is not made in vaine, becauſe it hath the promiſe of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:27718:30"/>
               <head>The fift Article of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dead.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHat ſay you of this fift article, of the reſurrection from the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what the reſurrection from the dead is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what vſe we may make of it.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is the reſurrection of the dead?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe death goeth before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, and life before death, therefore theſe three things may be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what life is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what death is.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, what reſurrection is.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is life, or what ſay you of life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. There is a double or a twofold life: one is called a naturall life, the other a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life, whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that there is a naturall and a ſpirituall man. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. verſ. 14, 15.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that which you call a naturall life?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:27718:30"/>
               <p>A. It may bee perceiued beſt by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects thereof in the three diuers ſorts of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning creatures.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, it is that which maketh graſſe, herbes, and trees to liue, grow, and flouriſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, it is that which giueth life and ſenſe to all brute creatures, as to fiſhes in the waters, to the foules of the aire, and to beaſts of the earth; for theſe doe not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liue, grow and flouriſh as the graſſe, hearbs and plants, with trees doe, but they haue ſenſe and feeling alſo, which the graſſe, hearbes, plants, and trees want.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, it is that which giueth vnto man not onely life, as vnto hearbes and trees, and ſenſe as vnto brute creatures, but alſo reaſon or vnderſtanding, which the two former ſorts of creatures want, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by man farre excelleth them. And it is the ſoule of man that giueth him this naturall life. And of this naturall life in theſe three ſorts of creatures, it ſeemeth <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake at <hi>Athens. Act.</hi> 17. verſ. 25. ſeeing he (that is God) giueth to all, life, and breath, and all things, ver. 28. for in him wee liue, and mooue, and haue our being.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>What is that which you call a ſpirituall life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> It is a ſupernaturall life which God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27718:31"/>gaue to <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency, ouer and beſides his naturall life.</p>
               <p>And that <hi>Adam</hi> in his firſt creation, and before his fall, had, beſides his naturall life, a ſupernaturall and a ſpirituall life, it may appeare by theſe foure reaſons.</p>
               <p>Firſt, after his fall hee loſt immediately this ſpirituall and ſupernaturall life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he had his naturall life, 930. yeares after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p>Secondly, before his fall hee had the tree of life for a ſigne or Sacrament of this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall life, but after his fall he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of it. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.22.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity, which are not tegenerate, want this ſupernaturall and ſpiritual life, which is called the life of God. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18. being alienated from the life of God, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this ſpirituall and ſupernaturall life, is reſtored to Gods elect againe in Chriſt, (who is our life. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.3.) when they are effectually called and regenerate.</p>
               <p>Now this ſupernaturall life of man, is the fruition of Gods comfortable and gratious preſence, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. for with thee is the well of life, and in thy light, ſhall wee ſee light.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, as the ſoule is the life of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27718:31"/>
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. euen ſo the gratious preſence of God is the ſupernaturall life of man.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>You haue ſhewed what life is, tell mee alſo what death is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Death is the depriuation of life, or the ſeparation and taking away of that thing which giueth life: as for example, take the ſoule from the body, and the body dyeth, for the body without the ſpirit is dead. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.26.</p>
               <p>And ſeparate the comfortable and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious preſence of God from man, and man dyeth, that is, loſeth his ſupernaturall life.</p>
               <p>There is nothing that ſeparateth Gods gracious preſence from man but ſinne, as <hi>Eſaias</hi> ſaith, your iniquities haue ſeparated betweene you and your God. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 59.2. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, all haue ſinned, and are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of the glory of God. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. and in an other place he ſaith, that the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Gentiles are without God in the world. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12</p>
               <p>Now it is manifeſt hereby that there are two ſorts or kinds of death.</p>
               <p>The firſt, is a ſpirituall death, which is the loſſe of the ſupernaturall life, when man is depriued of Gods comfortable and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preſence. And the death commeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men at two ſeuerall times. Firſt, when
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27718:32"/>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned all mankinde in him: for then all men dyed, as the Apoſtle ſaith. In <hi>Adam</hi> all die. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. and are alienated from the life of God. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. And this is the firſt ſpirituall death and may ſo be called. Secondly, at the day of iudgement, when all the reprobate only ſhall be caſt out of Gods gratious preſence, into vtter darkeneſſe, and further bee puniſhed with euerlaſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. And this is called the ſecond death. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is a naturall death, which is the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body, when the bodie dieth and returneth to the earth againe.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Now you haue ſhewed what life is, and what death is, ſhew alſo what the reſurrection of the dead is?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Reſurrection of the dead is nothing elſe but reſtitution to life againe. And man is reſtored from death to life at two times, and ſo there are two reſurrections.</p>
               <p>The firſt reſurrection is from the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all death, vnto the ſupernaturall life againe.</p>
               <p>And this firſt reſurrection is of the elect only, when they are raiſed vp from the death of ſinne, (into which they fell in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>) vnto the life of grace and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which is done in this life, at the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27718:32"/>time of their effectuall calling, conuerſion, and regeneration according to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.25. Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, the houre ſhall come and now is, when the dead (in ſinne) ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of God: and they that heare it ſhall liue. And the Apoſtle ſaith thus, awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.14.</p>
               <p>And this is called the firſt reſurrection. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.6.</p>
               <p>The ſecond reſurrection is of the bodies of all men out of their graues, and from their naturall death, which ſhall be at the great and generall day of iudgement. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2. And many of them that ſlept in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, and ſome to ſhame and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting contempt, ſo ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.28. Marueile not at this: for the houre is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the which all that are in the ground ſhall heare his voyce, and ſhall come forth, they that haue done good, vnto the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of life, and they that haue done euill vnto the reſurrection of death.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Now that you haue ſhewed that there are two reſurrections from the dead, tell mee which of them is meant in this fift Article?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> In the fift Article we muſt vnderſtand
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27718:33"/>that the Apoſtle ſpeaketh of the ſecond re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection which is of the bodies of all men out of their graues, and therefore of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the faithfull at the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And that this Article is to be taken and vnderſtood of the ſecond reſurrection of the Saints, and not of the firſt, theſe three reaſons ſhew.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the firſt reſurrrection was neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtood in the two firſt Articles, for there cannot bee repentance from dead workes, nor faith in God without effectuall calling and regeneration, or riſing from the death of ſinne to the life of grace.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the firſt reſurrection goeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies before baptiſme in conuerts, to whom this Catechiſme was more eſpecially at that time directed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this reſurrection in this fift Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, followeth after baptiſme, and ſhall bee accompliſhed at the laſt day of iudgement.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>Now that you haue ſpoken of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from the dead, what vſe will you make of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Becauſe the article is vnderſtood as the other articles alſo are of the faithfull, it may ſerue to teach them theſe three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, not to feare any thing that may
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:27718:33"/>happen to them in this life, as death, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, calamitie, &amp;c. Death is not fearefull to the faithfull becauſe it is but a ſleepe, it is written of <hi>Steuen</hi> when hee was ſtoned, that he fell a ſleepe. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that the faithfull being dead doe ſleepe. 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.13. <hi>Eſaias</hi> ſaith they reſt in their beds, <hi>Eſai.</hi> 57.2. wherefore the <hi>Graecians</hi> called the place of buriall <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>coemit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> or <hi>dormitorium</hi> in Latine, that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleeping place.</p>
               <p>Perſecution is not to bee feared becauſe it toucheth but the body onely <hi>Math.</hi> 10.28. feare not them which kill the body, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Aduerſitie and calamitie which happeneth to men in this life, is not to bee feared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is but temporarie, and the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection will be ioyfull; thus <hi>Iob</hi> in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of his calamitie comforted himſelfe with aſſured hope of reſurrection from the dead. <hi>Iob</hi> 19.25. for I know my redeemer liueth, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly to prepare themſelues faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to diſcharge the duties of their calling, and waite continually for the appearing of Chriſt to iudgement. For ſo Chriſt hauing foretold the time of his ſecond comming exhorteth, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.45. who then is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and wiſe ſeruant, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:27718:34"/>3. Thirdly, to confute the errours of them which firſt denied the reſurrection of the dead, as did the Saduces, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.23. <hi>Act.</hi> 23.8. as did Epicures and Atheiſts. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.19. as did <hi>Altades</hi> the 12. King of Aſſyria, <hi>Beroſus lib.</hi> 5. and ſome at Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12.32. ſecondly, ſaid the reſurrection was already paſt, as did <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus.</hi> 2. Tim. 2.18.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <head>The ſixt Article of eternall iudgement.</head>
               <p>Queſtion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHat will you ſay concerning this ſixe Article which is of eternall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, how it is called an eternall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> Three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, how it is called an eternall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I will note foure things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this eternall iudgement.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſome vſe to be made of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>How or why is this iudgement called eternall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The reaſon hereof will appeare, if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27718:34"/>we conſider theſe three ſorts of Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and compare them together, euen theſe three.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, a conditionall iudgement threatened.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, is a temporall iudgement executed.</p>
               <p>The third is, an eternall iudgement pronounced, and executed or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>The conditionall iudgement,
<note n="1" place="margin">
                     <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </note> is that which God threateneth with condition of repentance, that except the people againſt whom he threateneth iudgment do repent, he will powre his threatened iudgement vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but if the people repent, the Lord will turne away his iudgement from them, ſo the Lord himſelfe telleth vs. <hi>Ierm.</hi> 18.7. At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeake concerning a nation and concerning a kingdome, to plucke vp and to pull downe and to deſtroy it. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. If that nation againſt whom I haue pronounced, turne from their euill, I will repent of the euill that I thought to to doe vnto them. The iudgements which God threatneth generally againſt the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours of His Law. <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 26. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. &amp;c. <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> 18. <hi>verſe</hi> 15. &amp;c. conteine in them a condition of repentance
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:27718:35"/>as euery one may ſee that readeth thoſe two chapters.</p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Ionah</hi> threatened a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall iudgement againſt <hi>Nineueh</hi> that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fortie dayes it ſhould be deſtroyed.
<note n="2" place="margin">Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> 
                  <hi>Ionah</hi> 3.4. And that this iudgement was denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced conditionally it appeareth in that the people repented. <hi>Ionah</hi> 3.5. And in that the Lord turned away that iudgement. <hi>Ion.</hi> 3.10. Chriſt alſo ſheweth vs that ſome of Gods iudgements are conditionall, ſaying, except yee repent, yee ſhall all likewiſe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Luke</hi> 13.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The temporall iudgement is, that which God executeth vpon his diſobedient people, when they doe not repent at the hearing of his conditionall iudgements de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them. For then the Lord maketh a decree, <hi>Zephan.</hi> 2.2. that he will not turne away his threatned iudgement, no not if <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhould intreat him by earneſt prayer, <hi>Iere.</hi> 15.1. and if <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> were among thoſe impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinners, they ſhould deliuer but their owne ſoules by their righteouſneſſe, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 14.14. And yet this irreuocable iudgement is but temporall; for when the Lord hath executed it, then doth he in mercie returne to his people again with great compaſsion.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:27718:35"/>When the Prophet <hi>Eſayas cap.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had generally denounced the captiuitie of the Iewes in Babylon (which afterwards <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias cap.</hi> 25. deſcribed more particularly) and other calamities which they were to indure afterwards til Chriſts firſt comming in the fleſh; he ſhewed that iudgement, and thoſe calamities ſhould be but temporal and haue an end, ſaying, <hi>Eſay</hi> 40. verſe 1. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, comfort yee my people, ſaith your God. Verſe 2. Speake yee comfortably to Ieruſalem, and cry vnto her, that her war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare is accompliſhed, that her iniquitie is pardoned, for ſhee hath receiued of the Lords hand double for all her ſinnes; and in the reſt of his prophecie, from chap. 40. to the end, hee comforteth the Iewes with promiſes of deliuerance by <hi>Cyrus</hi> out of Babylon, as chap. 45.1. and by Chriſt out of miſeries, as chap. 54. The floud in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> was but a temporall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for afterwards the Lord reſtored the world againe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3 The eternall iudgement noteth three things; firſt,
<note n="3" place="margin">Eternall.</note> the great and laſt day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſecondly, the eternall ſentence that then ſhall be pronounced vpon the Elect for eternall ſaluation, and vpon the reprobate for eternall condemnation; thirdly, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27718:36"/>execution or performance of the ſentence then pronounced to giue euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life and happineſſe to the godly, and to puniſh the wicked with euerlaſting tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>And this is the eternall iudgement men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in this ſixt Article, and ſpecially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the godly for their euerlaſting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that whiles they are in this vale of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie, they ſhould comfort themſelues with continuall expectation of this eternall iudgement.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q. What be thoſe foure things which you ſaid you would obſerue concerning this eternall iudgement?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Firſt, the certaintie therof which may appeare.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe the Scripture ſaith, that God hath appointed a day, in the which hee will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.31.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Becauſe GOD is the Iudge of all the earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. and therefore it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, that hee will certainely iudge all the world.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Becauſe all men muſt be iudged, wee ſhall all ſtand before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.10.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the time thereof, which is;</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:27718:36"/>1 Foretolde in the Scripture, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To be ſearched out and deſired.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The time of this eternall iudgement is foretold, firſt, by Chriſt, ſecondly, by <hi>Paul,</hi> thirdly, by <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 Chriſt requeſted by his diſciples, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told this eternall iudgement, which ſhall be at his ſecond comming, and that twice ouer, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.</p>
               <p>Firſt, he foretelleth them of three things which ſhould come to paſſe, before his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond comming, which are theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1 Of the beginning of ſorrowes, as hee calleth them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. that is, of falſe Chriſts: <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. of watres. <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. of famine. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of the ten perſecutions, as it ſeemeth which began vnder <hi>Nero,</hi> and continued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the dayes of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> the great, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of the publike and free libertie of the Goſpel, that ſhould be vnder <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> the great. <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Secondly hee fore telleth them againe of three other things that ſhould alſo come to paſſe before his ſecond comming, that is, 1. of the deſtruction of Ieruſalem. <hi>ver.</hi> 15.2. of falſe Prophets as it were of thoſe heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks which aroſe in the Church after for along time. <hi>verſe</hi> 23.3. of Poperie. <hi>verſe.</hi>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:27718:37"/>29. for by the Sunne we may vnderſtand the word of God, by the Moone the Church; by the Starres, the Doctors that fell from the trueth; and by the powers of heauen, the truth and life of pure religion.</p>
               <p>Thus wee preſume to ſhew what may be the meaning of the Chriſts propheſie in that Chapter, with ſubmiſsion to the cenſure of the learned and religious.</p>
               <p>And after theſe things thus foretold are come to paſſe, then will Chriſt come the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to this eternall iudgment. <hi>verſe.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Paul</hi> withſtanding falſe teachers, which ſayd that the ſecond comming of Chriſt was at hand, telleth the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> of three things that muſt come to paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt came to Iudgement, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that there muſt be an apoſtaſie and falling away. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that that wicked man of ſinne, that is the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be reucaled. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.8. which was done about 600. yeeres after Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that that man of ſinne, the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt bee conſumed with the ſpirit of Chriſts mouth, <hi>verſe.</hi> 8. that is, by the preaching of the word, as wee now ſee hee is, and hath beene for theſe 300. yeeres laſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:27718:37"/>paſt continually.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle in the booke of the reuelation. <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. &amp;c. doth plentifully foretell what ſhall come to paſſe before Chriſts ſecond comming, that the diligent reading and true vnderſtanding of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie may ſhew how neere wee are to this eternall iudgement, though wee may not ſearch after the day and houre of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.36.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This time of Chriſts comming to this eternall iudgement, thus foretolde, ought to be ſearched out, and longed for of all true Chriſtians, as <hi>Jacob</hi> waiting for the land of Canaan (which was a type of the kingdome of heauen, and which God had promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> after 430. yeeres were expired. <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.40. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.) required of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> that hee ſhould not burie him in <hi>Egypt,</hi> but carie him into the land of Canaan. <hi>Gen.</hi> 47.29.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Ioſeph</hi> tooke an oath of his brethren, that God brought them into the land of Canaan they ſhould carie his bones with them. <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.25. As the Iewes waited for their promiſed deliuerance out of 70. yeeres Captiuitie in Babylon. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. As <hi>Abraham, Ioh.</hi> 8.56. Prophets and Kings, <hi>Luke.</hi> 10.24.1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. and the Angels. 1.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27718:38"/>
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. waited for Chriſts firſt comming: ſo ſhould we waite for his ſecond comming. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. looking for that bleſſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3.
<note n="3" place="margin">Place.</note> Thirdly, the place thereof which is.</p>
               <p>Firſt, where Chriſt ſhall iudge all the world, that is, in the aire, for when Chriſt ſhall ſo deſcend, as he aſcended. <hi>Act.</hi> 2.11. then we which are aline, and remaine, ſhall be caught vp together with them (that is the dead) in the cloudes, to meete the Lord in the aire. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Secondly, where all perſons iudged, ſhall be, that is, ſome in heauen aboue, and ſome in hell belowe, for <hi>Salomon</hi> thus diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth theſe two places. <hi>Prou.</hi> 15.24. The way of life is aboue to the wiſe, that he may depart from hell beneath. And heauen eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in the Scripture is ſaide to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and it may ſuffice to ſay, hell is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, without any further inquire of it, till wee finde a more ſpeciall place of hell noted in the Scripture,</p>
               <p>Fourthly,
<note place="margin">A ſentence.</note> the iudgement then to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, or ſentene then to be pronounced, which is ſet downe. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. verſ. 34. Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit the kingdome
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27718:38"/>prepared for you from the foundation of the world. verſ. 41. Depart from me ye cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into euerlaſting fire, prepared for the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and his Angels. Then ſhall the godly be euer in glory with Chriſt where he is. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21, &amp; 22.</p>
               <p>Then ſhall the wicked euer bee with the diuell where he is, in vtter darkneſſe, where ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Math.</hi> 22.13. in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.8. where their worme dyeth not, and the fire is not quenched. <hi>Mark.</hi> 9.44.</p>
               <p>Q. <hi>You haue ſhewed which is the eternall iudgement, and foure things belonging to it, what vſe will you now make of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A. Fine inſtructions for the faithfull, to whom this article is properly applyed in this Catechiſme.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, that the faithfull continually waite for the comming of Chriſt to his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall iudgement that then they may inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite glory, he that hopeth for any earthly benefite of libertie, lands, goods, or ſuch like, waiteth continually for the time when he ſhall enioye his deſire, and counteth the yeares, moneths, and dayes: yea ſometimes the ſonne thinketh his father liueth too long, becauſe hee dayly deſires to inherite
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27718:39"/>his fathers poſſeſsions, and there is a crown of righteouſneſſe laide vp for all them that loue the appearing of Chriſt. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. then the faithfull ſhall be deliuered from all thoſe miſeries of continual labour, of many infirmities of outward afflictions, and of temporall or naturall death, which they are ſubiect to in this life, then ſhall they enioy the kingdome of heauen, the preſence of God, the ſocietie of Saints and Angels, the creature waiteth for this time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.19. The faithfull waite for this time, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. The holy Angels waite for this time, for as they waited for Chriſts firſt comming. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. ſo we ſuppoſe they looke for his ſecond comming. The Saints departed out of this life long for it. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Dauid</hi> waiteth for it. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.9. and 17.15. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee ought continually to waite for Chriſts comming.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, that the faithfull, who are brethren in Chriſt, and fellow heires of the kingdome of heauen, ought to loue one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, as the Apoſtle willeth. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.8. Owe no man any thing, but to loue one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, that the faithfull vſe all good meanes, which God hath ordained to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them to the attainement of euerlaſting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27718:39"/>life, for whatſoeuer a man deſireth, hee will endeauour to vſe all good meanes whereby he may attaine vnto it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, that the faithfull patiently beare all aduerſitie that happeneth to them in this preſent liſe, looking vnto Ieſus the authour and finiſher of our faith, who for the ioy that was ſet before him, endured the croſſe, deſpiſed the ſhame, and is ſet downe at the right hand of the throne of God. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. And conſidering that our light affliction which is but for a moment, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for vs a farre more exceeding and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall weight of glory. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fiftly, that the faithfull bee conſtant, bold, and couragious, alwayes to confeſſe &amp; profeſſe this their hope of eternall glory before men, whenſoeuer occaſion requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, being ready alwayes to giue an anſwer to euery man that asketh a reaſon of the hope they haue in God. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. and ſay with the Apoſtle. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. If God be for vs, who can be againſt vs, &amp;c. then will Chriſt alſo confeſſe them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Father which is in heauen. <hi>Math.</hi> 10.32.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
